Guide to Fulton-Wheatland Family Correspondence
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Fulton-Wheatland Family Correspondence
1921-1930
1923-1925
Ms Coll 38
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
(2 boxes)
Lucia Pickering Wheatland married John Fulton, who was in Oxford on a Rhodes fellowship, in 1923. The collection contains correspondence from Lucia and John Fulton in Oxford to Lucia's parents, Richard and Mary Wheatland, in Massachusetts. John Fulton was named professor of physiology at Yale in 1929.
Fulton, Lucia Pickering, 1899-1989
Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Elizabeth Davey from the estate of Lycurgus M. Davey, M.D., 2009.
Custodial History
Lycurgus Davey, a neurosurgeon and member of the Yale Medical faculty, was a graduate of Yale College (1939) and Yale School of Medicine (1943). These letters were probably lent by Lucia Fulton to Dr. Davey who wrote historical articles on Fulton.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
John Farquhar Fulton papers, MS 1238, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library; John Farquhar Fulton papers in the Medical Historical Library, Ms Coll 2, Cushing/Whitney Medical Library.
Biographical / Historical
Lucia Wheatland was born on June 26, 1899, in Salem, Massachusetts, the daughter of Richard and Mary Robinson Wheatland. She grew up at her parents' country home in Topsfield, near Salem, and attended Milton Academy. Through her brother Stephen Wheatland who attended Harvard College, she met John F. Fulton. Fulton, who graduated from Harvard College in 1921, received a Rhodes Scholarship to Oxford. Lucia Wheatland married John Fulton in Oxford on September 29, 1923. As a Rhodes Fellow, John Fulton spent two years at Magdalen College, Oxford, and then a further two years at Oxford as a Christopher Welch Scholar and demonstrator in physiology. He worked under the neurophysiologist, Charles Sherrington. The Fultons lived around the corner from Lady Grace Revere Osler, widow of Sir William Osler, who lived at 13 Norham Gardens. Lady Osler offered her hospitality, mentored Lucia Fulton in household management and entertaining, and made Osler's book collection freely available to John Fulton. Fulton received a B.A. from Oxford in 1923, and an M.A. and D. Phil. in 1925. In the summer of 1925, the Fultons returned to Boston where John Fulton received his M.D. at Harvard Medical School in 1927. In 1927-1928 Fulton worked under Harvey Cushing as an associate neurological fellow at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston. The Fultons returned to Oxford in 1928, where John Fulton was a fellow at Magdalen College. Fulton was appointed professor of physiology at Yale in 1929.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of frequent handwritten letters from Lucia and/or John Fulton in Oxford (or while traveling) to Lucia's parents at Topsfield, Massachusetts. Most of letters were written by Lucia to her mother, Mary Robinson Wheatland (Mrs. Richard Wheatland), but some were addressed to her father or to both parents. Some letters were written by John Fulton to the Wheatlands. The first group of letters date from just before the Fultons' marriage in 1923 to the Fultons' return to the United States in the summer of 1925. A second group of letters dates from the Fultons' second stay in Oxford in 1928-1929. Letters discuss social life in Oxford, management of the household and household purchases, family news, and travels. Some letters relate to John Fulton's work with Sherrington and his interests in book collecting and history of medicine. There are also several letters in the collection from Lucia Fulton to her brother David P. Wheatland in Bangor, Maine, and from Lady Grace Revere Osler to Mrs. Wheatland. The few snapshot photographs enclosed in letters in this collection are of houses or travel scenery.
Arrangement
Organized in two series: 1. Lucia and John Fulton letters to the Wheatland family. 2. Other correspondence and miscellany.
Medicine -- History; Neurophysiology; Physiology; Oxford (England) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Photographs; Postcards; Book collectors; Medical historians; Neurophysiologists; Physiologists; Osler, Grace Revere Gross, Lady; Sherrington, Charles Scott, Sir, 1857-1952; Wheatland, David P.; Wheatland, Mary Robinson; Wheatland, Richard; Wheatland family; Magdalen College (University of Oxford); University of Oxford -- Rhodes scholarships
- Lucia and John Fulton letters to the Wheatland family, Series I
  - Lucia Wheatland, Boston, to John Fulton, traveling in Europe, 1922 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admission card for Mrs. Wheatland to the Ladies Gallery of the Rhodes Trustees' Dinner, 1923 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    On reverse, comments presumably by Mrs. Wheatland, on the speeches.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1923 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1923 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1923 November-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    One letter from Lucia Fulton is addressed to "Grandma."
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes a letter from Ethel Sherrington, wife of Charles Sherrington, to Mrs. Wheatland.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes a letter from Edith Fulton, John Fulton's mother, to Mrs. Wheatland.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 August (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 September (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 October (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes a letter from Joan Liddell to Lucia Fulton.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 November (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes a letter from Martha Wheatland (Lucia's younger sister who was staying with the Fultons) to [Lucia Fulton].
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1924 December (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 January (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 February (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 March (Box 2, Folder 20)
    One letter includes a snapshot of a home for rent.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 April (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Inlcudes a letter from Charoline[?] E. Williams to Lucia Fulton.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Includes an invitation to the opening, the program, and a description of the Lewis Evans Collection of Scientific Instruments installed in the Ashmolean Museum.
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 June (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1925 July (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1928 June (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1928 July (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lucia and John Fulton to the Wheatlands, 1928 November-December (Box 2, Folder 27)
    The Wheatlands had been previously visiting the Fultons. Includes letters from Joan Liddell from S & M(?) to Lucia Fulton, and from Margaret A. Revere to Mrs. Wheatland.
  - Lucia Fulton to her mother, 1929 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Mentions forthcoming move to New Haven.
  - Lucia Fulton to David P. Wheatland, Bangor, Maine, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    David P. Wheatland was Lucia Fulton's brother. One letter discussed John Fulton's laboratory equipment and includes an annotated recording by Fulton of muscle movement.
- Other correspondence and miscellany
  - Eleanore Jane Fulton, Lancaster, Pennsylvania, to John Fulton, 1921 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    A distant relation responding to John Fulton's interest in the history of the Fulton family.
  - Grace Revere Osler to Mrs. (Mary) Wheatland, 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Joan Liddell to Mrs. (Mary) Wheatland, 1928 January 10 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Miscellany found with the collection (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Clipped short poems, refrain from a Jacobite song, and holiday card from the Fulton's New Haven home.